In the mid-'90s,
في منتصف سنوات التسعينات
the CDC and Kaiser Permanente
كشف مركز السيطرة على الأمراض ومؤسسة كايزر
discovered an exposure that dramatically increased the risk
عن تعرض زاد بشكل مأساوي احتمال
for seven out of 10 of the leading causes of death in the United States.
على سبعة من كل عشرة أسباب مؤدّية للموت في الولايات المتّحدة
In high doses, it affects brain development,
الجرعات المرتفعة، تؤثر على نمو الدماغ
the immune system, hormonal systems,
الجهاز المناعي، والأنظمة الهرمونية،
and even the way our DNA is read and transcribed.
وحتى الطريقة التي يقرأ و ينسخ بها حمضنا النووي DNA
Folks who are exposed in very high doses
الأشخاص الذين يتعرضون لها بجرعات عالية جدا
have triple the lifetime risk of heart disease and lung cancer
يتضاعف ثلاث مرات خطر إصابتهم بأمراض القلب وسرطان الرئة
and a 20-year difference in life expectancy.
وينقص متوسط أعمارهم بعشرين سنة
And yet, doctors today are not trained in routine screening or treatment.
وحتى الآن، الأطباء ليسوا مدربين اليوم في الفحص أو العلاج الروتيني.
Now, the exposure I'm talking about is not a pesticide or a packaging chemical.
الآن، المشكل الذي أتحدث عنه ليس مبيد حشرات أو مواد كيميائية
It's childhood trauma.
إنها صدمة الطفولة
Okay. What kind of trauma am I talking about here?
حسنا، عن أي نوع من الصدمات أتكلم ؟
I'm not talking about failing a test or losing a basketball game.
أنا لا أتكلم عن الفشل في امتحان وخسارة مبارة لكرة السلّة
I am talking about threats that are so severe or pervasive
أنا أتكلم عن التهديدات التي كثرت حدّتها وانتشارها
that they literally get under our skin and change our physiology:
التي تتوغّل داخل جلدنا وتغير وظائف أعضاء جسمنا
things like abuse or neglect,
أشياء مثل سوء المعاملة والإهمال
or growing up with a parent who struggles with mental illness
أو النشوء داخل بيت يكافح فيه أحد الوالدين ضدّ مرض عقلي
or substance dependence.
أو إدمان المخدّرات
Now, for a long time,
الآن، ولفترة طويلة
I viewed these things in the way I was trained to view them,
راقبت هذه الأمور بطريقة كنت قد تدرّبتُ على رؤيتها
either as a social problem -- refer to social services --
إمّا كمشكل اجتماعي - الرجوع لخدمات الاجتماعية-
or as a mental health problem -- refer to mental health services.
أو كمشكل يرتبط بالصحة العقلية - الرجوع لخدمات الصحّة العقلية-
And then something happened to make me rethink my entire approach.
ثم حدث أمر جعلني أعيد التفكير في مقاربتي
When I finished my residency,
عندما انتهيت من فترة تدريبي،
I wanted to go someplace where I felt really needed,
وأردت الذهاب إلى مكان حيث أحِسُّ أن هناك من يحتاجني
someplace where I could make a difference.
إلى مكان أستطيع فيه أن أصنع الفرق
So I came to work for California Pacific Medical Center,
ولهذا قدِمتُ إلى مركز كاليفورنيا الطبي المحيط الهادئ
one of the best private hospitals in Northern California,
أحد أفضل المستشفيات الخاصّة في شمال كاليفورنيا
and together, we opened a clinic in Bayview-Hunters Point,
ومعاً قمنا بافتتاح مصحّة في - باي فيو هانترز-
one of the poorest, most underserved neighborhoods in San Francisco.
في أحد أفقر وأكثر أحياء سان فرانسيسكو تهميشا
Now, prior to that point,
الآن، وقبل هذه النقطة
there had been only one pediatrician in all of Bayview
كان هناك طبيب أطفال وحيد في حي -باي فيو- كله
to serve more than 10,000 children,
لخدمة أكثر من عشرة آلاف طفل
so we hung a shingle, and we were able to provide top-quality care
بدأنا العمل، وكنّا قادرين على منح أفضل رعاية طبية
regardless of ability to pay.
بغض النظر عن القدرة على دفع المستحقات
It was so cool. We targeted the typical health disparities:
كان الأمر رائعا، استهدفنا التفاوتات الصحية النموذجية
access to care, immunization rates, asthma hospitalization rates,
الولوج إلى الرعاية الصحية، معدلات التطعيم معدلات علاج الربو
and we hit all of our numbers.
وتجاوزنا كل أرقامنا
We felt very proud of ourselves.
وشعرنا بالفخر بأنفسنا
But then I started noticing a disturbing trend.
ثم بدأت بملاحظة اتّجاه مزعج
A lot of kids were being referred to me for ADHD,
توجيه الكثير من الأطفال بسبب ADHD
or Attention Deficit Hyperactivity Disorder,
أي اضطراب نقص الانتباه مع فرط النشاط
but when I actually did a thorough history and physical,
ولكن عندما قمت بمراقبة معمقة للسجلات والملفات
what I found was that for most of my patients,
ما وجدته أن أغلب مرضاي
I couldn't make a diagnosis of ADHD.
لم أستطع أن أقوم بتشخيص لل ADHD
Most of the kids I was seeing had experienced such severe trauma
أغلب الأطفال الذين عاينتهم عاشوا تجارب صدمات حادة
that it felt like something else was going on.
التي تجعلك تحس أن شيئا آخر يجري
Somehow I was missing something important.
بشكلٍ ما أغفلت أمراً مهمّاً
Now, before I did my residency, I did a master's degree in public health,
الآن، قبل تدريبي حصلت على درجة الماجستير في الصحة العامة،
and one of the things that they teach you in public health school
واحدة من الأشياء التي يعلمونها لك في مدرسة الصحة العامة
is that if you're a doctor
هي أنك إذا كنت طبيباً
and you see 100 kids that all drink from the same well,
وترى 100 طفل يشربون من نفس البئر
and 98 of them develop diarrhea,
و98 منهم تعرضوا للإسهال
you can go ahead and write that prescription
يمكنك المضي قدماً وكتابة هذه الوصفة
for dose after dose after dose of antibiotics,
جرعة بعد جرعة بعد جرعة من المضادّات الحيوية
or you can walk over and say, "What the hell is in this well?"
أو أن تذهب فوقها وتقول : "ماهذا الجحيم في هذه البئر"
So I began reading everything that I could get my hands on
ثم بدأت أقرأ كل شيء تقع عليه يدي
about how exposure to adversity
حول كيف أن التعرض للعنف
affects the developing brains and bodies of children.
يؤثر على نمو أدمغة وأجسام الأطفال
And then one day, my colleague walked into my office,
وفي أحد الأيام ، دخل زميلي إلى مكتبي
and he said, "Dr. Burke, have you seen this?"
وقال: "د. بورك، هل رأيت هذا؟"
In his hand was a copy of a research study
وفي يده نسخة من دراسة بحثية
called the Adverse Childhood Experiences Study.
اسمها دراسة تجارب التعرض للعنف في الطفولة
That day changed my clinical practice and ultimately my career.
هذا اليوم غيّر ممارساتي السريرية و بشكل أهم مساري المهني
The Adverse Childhood Experiences Study
دراسة تجارب التعرض للعنف في الطفولة
is something that everybody needs to know about.
إنها أمر يجب على الجميع معرفته
It was done by Dr. Vince Felitti at Kaiser and Dr. Bob Anda at the CDC,
قام بها الدكتور "فيـنس فيليـتي" من كايزر ود. بوب أندا من مركز السيطرة على الأمراض
and together, they asked 17,500 adults about their history of exposure
ومعاً قاما بطرح أسئلة على 175,000 بالغاً حول قصصهم في التعرض
to what they called "adverse childhood experiences," or ACEs.
لما يسمى "تجارب التعرض للعنف في الطفولة" أو ACE
Those include physical, emotional, or sexual abuse;
وتشمل العنف الجسدي والعاطفي أو الانتهاك الجنسي
physical or emotional neglect;
أو الإهمال الجسدي أو العاطفي
parental separation or divorce;
اتفصال الوالدين أو الطلاق
or domestic violence.
العنف المنزلي
For every yes, you would get a point on your ACE score.
في كل إجابة ب"نعم" يحصل المتطوع على نقطة في نتيجة ACE
And then what they did
وهذا ما كانا يفعلانه
was they correlated these ACE scores against health outcomes.
ثم يربطان نتيجة ACE بالنتائج الصحيّة
What they found was striking.
وما وجداه كان لافتا للنظر
Two things:
أمران:
Number one, ACEs are incredibly common.
الأول : نتائج ACE متقاربة بشكل لا يصدّق
Sixty-seven percent of the population had at least one ACE,
67% من المتطوعين لديهم على الأقل نقطة ACE واحدة
and 12.6 percent, one in eight, had four or more ACEs.
12,6% أي واحد من كل ثمانية أشخاص لديهم على الأقل 4 نقط ACE
The second thing that they found
الأمر الثاني الذي وجداه
was that there was a dose-response relationship
هو أن هناك علاقة جرعة واستجابة
between ACEs and health outcomes:
بين ACE والنتائج الصحية
the higher your ACE score, the worse your health outcomes.
كلما زادت نقط ACE كلما كانت النتائج الصحية أسوأ
For a person with an ACE score of four or more,
بالنسبة لشخص لديه أربع نقط ACE أو أكثر
their relative risk of chronic obstructive pulmonary disease
مخاطرها المتصلة بأمراض الانسداد الرئوي المزمن
was two and a half times that of someone with an ACE score of zero.
تتضاعف مرتين ونصف مقارنة بشخص لديه صفر نقطة ACE
For hepatitis, it was also two and a half times.
وبالنسبة لالتهاب الكبد تتضاعف مرّتين ونصف أيضا
For depression, it was four and a half times.
الكآبة اربع مرّات ونصف
For suicidality, it was 12 times.
بالنسبة للانتحار كانت 12 مرة
A person with an ACE score of seven or more
وشخص لديه سبع نقط ACE أو أكثر
had triple the lifetime risk of lung cancer
معرض ثلاث مرات لخطر الأصابة بسرطان الرئة
and three and a half times the risk of ischemic heart disease,
وثلاث مرات ونصف لمرض القلب الإقفاري
the number one killer in the United States of America.
أول سبب للوفيات في الولايات المتحدة الأمريكية
Well, of course this makes sense.
بالطبع هذا الأمر يبدو معقولا تماما
Some people looked at this data and they said, "Come on.
بعض الناس يرون هذه المعلومات ويقولون:
You have a rough childhood, you're more likely to drink and smoke
"هيّا، لقد عشت طفولة قاسية كنت أكثر عرضة للشرب والتدخين
and do all these things that are going to ruin your health.
وتفعل كل هذه الأشياء التي ستدمّر صحّتك
This isn't science. This is just bad behavior."
إنها ليست علماً إنها فقط تصرف سيئ
It turns out this is exactly where the science comes in.
اتضح أنّ هذا هو بالضبط حيث يأتي العلم فيما بعد
We now understand better than we ever have before
الآن نفهم أفضل من السابق
how exposure to early adversity
كيف أن التعرض المبكر للعنف
affects the developing brains and bodies of children.
يؤثر على نموّ أدمغة وأجسام الأطفال
It affects areas like the nucleus accumbens,
وتؤثر على مناطق كالنواة المتكئة
the pleasure and reward center of the brain
مركز السعادة و المكافأة في الدماغ
that is implicated in substance dependence.
التي تورطت في إدمان المخدّرات
It inhibits the prefrontal cortex,
ويمنع قشرة الفصّ الجبهي
which is necessary for impulse control and executive function,
الضرورية للسيطرة على الانفعالات والوظائف التنفيذية
a critical area for learning.
المنطقة الحساسة للتعلّم
And on MRI scans,
وفي فحوصات الرنين المغناطيسي
we see measurable differences in the amygdala,
نرى فرقا واضحا في اللوزة الدماغية
the brain's fear response center.
مركز الاستجابة للخوف في الدماغ
So there are real neurologic reasons
ولذلك هناك أسباب عصبية حقيقية
why folks exposed to high doses of adversity
لماذا يعتبر الأشخاص المتعرضون للعنف بجرعات كبيرة
are more likely to engage in high-risk behavior,
هم أكثر عرضة للانخراط في السلوكيات عالية المخاطر
and that's important to know.
وهذا مهم لنعرفه
But it turns out that even if you don't engage in any high-risk behavior,
ولكن اتضح أنه حتى لو كنت لا تنخرط في أي سلوكيات عالية المخاطر
you're still more likely to develop heart disease or cancer.
فأنت لا تزال معرضا للإصابة بأمراض القلب والسرطان
The reason for this has to do with the hypothalamic–pituitary–adrenal axis,
والسبب في هذا له علاقة بمحور الغدة النخامية، الغدة الكظرية
the brain's and body's stress response system
وهو نظام الاستجابة للتوتر في الدماغ والجسم
that governs our fight-or-flight response.
الذي يحكم تجاوبنا مع التهديدات والمشاكل
How does it work?
كيف تعمل ؟
Well, imagine you're walking in the forest and you see a bear.
حسناً، تخيّل أنك تتنزه في الغابة ورأيت دُبّـاً
Immediately, your hypothalamus sends a signal to your pituitary,
على الفور، سيرسل المهاد (hypothalamus) إشارة إلى غدّتك النخامية
which sends a signal to your adrenal gland that says,
التي ترسل بدورها إشارة إلى غدّتك الكظرية تقول فيها:
"Release stress hormones! Adrenaline! Cortisol!"
"الافراج عن هرمونات التوتر! الأدرينالين! الكورتيزول! "
And so your heart starts to pound,
وهكذا سيبدأ قلبك يخفق بشدّة
Your pupils dilate, your airways open up,
ويتسع بؤبؤ عينك و تفتح مجاريك التنفسية
and you are ready to either fight that bear or run from the bear.
فتكون مستعداً إما للمواجهة الدّب أو الهرب منه
And that is wonderful
وهذا شيء مذهل
if you're in a forest and there's a bear.
هذا إذا كنت في غابة وهناك دبّ
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
But the problem is what happens when the bear comes home every night,
ولكن المشكل يحصل إذا كان الدّبّ يأتي إلى البيت كلّ ليلة
and this system is activated over and over and over again,
وبتم تنشيط هذا الجهاز أكثر وأكثر وأكثر مراراً
and it goes from being adaptive, or life-saving,
وتتغير من كونها للتكيف والحفاظ على الحياة
to maladaptive, or health-damaging.
لتصبح ضدّ التكيف ومدمّراً للصحة
Children are especially sensitive to this repeated stress activation,
الأطفال حساسون بشكل ٍ خاص لهذا التنشيط المتكرر للتوتر
because their brains and bodies are just developing.
لأن أدمغتهم وأجسامهم في طور التكوين
High doses of adversity not only affect brain structure and function,
الجرعات المرتفعة من العنف لا تؤثر فقط في بنية الدماغ ووظائفه
they affect the developing immune system,
بل تؤثر في نمو الجهاز المناعي
developing hormonal systems,
نمو الأنظمة الهرمونية
and even the way our DNA is read and transcribed.
وحتى الطريقة التي يقرأ وينسخ حمضنا النووي DNA
So for me, this information threw my old training out the window,
بالنسبة لي، هذه المعلومة جعلتني أرمي تدريباتي السابقة من النافذة
because when we understand the mechanism of a disease,
لأننا عندما نفهم آليّة مرض ما
when we know not only which pathways are disrupted, but how,
عندما نعرف ليس فقط أي مسارات تعطّلت، ولكن أيضاً كيف،
then as doctors, it is our job to use this science
وكأطِبّاء فإنّ عَمَلَنا أن نستعمل هذا العلم
for prevention and treatment.
للوقاية والعلاج
That's what we do.
وهذا ما نفعله
So in San Francisco, we created the Center for Youth Wellness
في سان فرانسيسكو، أنشأنا "مركز صحة الشباب"
to prevent, screen and heal the impacts of ACEs and toxic stress.
لوقاية وفحص و علاج مخلفات العنف ضد الأطفال (ACE) والتوتر السام
We started simply with routine screening of every one of our kids
بدأنا ببساطة مع الفحص الروتيني كل واحد من أطفالنا
at their regular physical,
في قدراتهم البدنية العادية،
because I know that if my patient has an ACE score of 4,
لأنني أعلم أنه إذا كان مجموع نقط ACE لمريضي يتجاوز 4 نقط
she's two and a half times as likely to develop hepatitis or COPD,
ترفع مرتين ونصف احتمال الإصابة التهاب الكبد أو مرض الانسداد الرئوي المزمن،
she's four and half times as likely to become depressed,
إنها أربعة ونصف أضعاف احتمال الاصابة بالاكتئاب
and she's 12 times as likely to attempt to take her own life
يرتفع احتمال الانتحار 12 مرة
as my patient with zero ACEs.
مقارنة مع مريض آخر رصيده صفر نقطة ACE
I know that when she's in my exam room.
أعلم أنها عندما تكون في غرفة الفحص
For our patients who do screen positive,
بالنسبة لمرضانا الذين تكون نتيجة فحصهم إيجابية
we have a multidisciplinary treatment team that works to reduce the dose of adversity
لدينا فريق معالجة متعدد التخصصات يعمل على تقليل جرعة العنف
and treat symptoms using best practices, including home visits, care coordination,
وعلاج الأعراض باستخدام أفضل الممارسات بما في ذلك الزيارات المنزلية، وتنسيق الرعاية،
mental health care, nutrition,
الرعاية الصحية النفسية، والتغذية
holistic interventions, and yes, medication when necessary.
التدخلات الشاملة، ونعم، الدواء عند الضرورة.
But we also educate parents about the impacts of ACEs and toxic stress
ولكن قمنا أيضا بتوعية الآباء حول تأثيرات العنف في الطفولة والتوتر الحاد
the same way you would for covering electrical outlets, or lead poisoning,
وبنفس أهميّة تغطية المنافذ الكهربائية، أو التسمم بالرصاص
and we tailor the care of our asthmatics and our diabetics
ثم أسسنا لرعاية مرضانا المصابين بالربو ومرض السكري
in a way that recognizes that they may need more aggressive treatment,
بطريقة ندرك أنها قد تحتاج إلى علاج أكثر عدوانية
given the changes to their hormonal and immune systems.
نظرا للتغيرات في الأنظمة الهرمونية والجهاز المناعي.
So the other thing that happens when you understand this science
وبالتالي فإن الشيء الآخر الذي يحدث عند فهم هذا العلم
is that you want to shout it from the rooftops,
هو أنك تريد أن تصرخ به من فوق أسطح المنازل
because this isn't just an issue for kids in Bayview.
لأن هذه ليست مجرد قضية للأطفال في - باي فيو-
I figured the minute that everybody else heard about this,
تطلّعتُ إلى تلك اللحظة التي يسمع فيها كل شخص آخر بهذا
it would be routine screening, multi-disciplinary treatment teams,
سيكون الفحص الروتيني، فرق معالجة متعددة التخصصات،
and it would be a race to the most effective clinical treatment protocols.
وسيكون سباق نحو أكثر بروتوكولات العلاج السريري فعالية.
Yeah. That did not happen.
نعم. لكن هذا لم يحدث
And that was a huge learning for me.
وكان ذلك درسا عظيما لي
What I had thought of as simply best clinical practice
ما كنت أعتقد أنه ببساطة أفضل الممارسات السريرية
I now understand to be a movement.
الآن أنا أفهم ما معنى أن تكون حركة
In the words of Dr. Robert Block,
على حد قول الدكتور روبرت بلوك
the former President of the American Academy of Pediatrics,
الرئيس السابق للأكاديمية الأمريكية لطب الأطفال
"Adverse childhood experiences
"تجارب العنف ضد الطفولة
are the single greatest unaddressed public health threat
هي إحدى أخطر التهديدات غير المعالجة على الصحة العامة
facing our nation today."
التي تواجه أمتنا اليوم"
And for a lot of people, that's a terrifying prospect.
وبالنسبة للكثير من الناس، هذا مخيف
The scope and scale of the problem seems so large that it feels overwhelming
نطاق وحجم المشكلة يبدو كبيرا بحيث يشعرك أنه يغمرك
to think about how we might approach it.
لنفكر كيف يمكننا وضع مقاربة له
But for me, that's actually where the hopes lies,
ولكن بالنسبة لي، هذا هو الواقع حيث تكمن الآمال
because when we have the right framework,
لأن عندما يكون لدينا الإطار الصحيح
when we recognize this to be a public health crisis,
عندما نعترف أن هذه أزمة صحة عامة
then we can begin to use the right tool kit to come up with solutions.
وبعد ذلك يمكننا البدء في استخدام الأدوات الصحيحة من أجل التوصل إلى حلول
From tobacco to lead poisoning to HIV/AIDS,
من التبغ إلى التسمم بالرصاص إلى فيروس نقص المناعة البشرية / الإيدز
the United States actually has quite a strong track record
الولايات المتحدة تملك حاليا سجلا قويا
with addressing public health problems,
مع معالجة مشاكل الصحة العامة
but replicating those successes with ACEs and toxic stress
لكن تكرار تلك النجاحات مع إدخالACE (تجارب العنف في الطفولة) والتوتر الحاد
is going to take determination and commitment,
سيصبح قراراً والتزاماً
and when I look at what our nation's response has been so far,
وعندما أنظر إلى مدي تجاوب أمّتنا
I wonder,
أستغرب
why haven't we taken this more seriously?
لماذا لم نأخذ الأمر على محمل الجدّ ؟
You know, at first I thought that we marginalized the issue
تعلمون، في البداية ظننت أننا وضعنا القضية على الهامش
because it doesn't apply to us.
لأنها لا تنطبق علينا.
That's an issue for those kids in those neighborhoods.
وهذا يمثل مشكلة بالنسبة لهؤلاء الأطفال في تلك الأحياء.
Which is weird, because the data doesn't bear that out.
وهذا غريب، لأن البيانات لا تؤكد ذلك
The original ACEs study was done in a population
الذراسة الأصلية حول تجارب العنف في الطفولة -ACE- تمت على متطوعين
that was 70 percent Caucasian,
70% منهم قوقازيون
70 percent college-educated.
70٪ منهم تلقوا تعليما جامعيا
But then, the more I talked to folks,
ولكن بعد ذلك، كلما تحدثت أكثر إلى الناس
I'm beginning to think that maybe I had it completely backwards.
بدأت أعتقد أنني ربما أتراجع إلى الوراء
If I were to ask how many people in this room
إذا كان لي أن أسأل كم عدد الناس في هذه القاعة
grew up with a family member who suffered from mental illness,
نشأ مع أحد أفراد الأسرة الذين عانوا من مرض عقلي،
I bet a few hands would go up.
أراهن أن قليلا من الأيدي سترتفع
And then if I were to ask how many folks had a parent who maybe drank too much,
ثم إذا كان لي أن أسأل كم شخصا كان أحد والديه يشرب ربما أكثر من اللازم
or who really believed that if you spare the rod, you spoil the child,
أو من يعتقد حقاً أنك إذا تخليت عن العقاب ستفسد الولد
I bet a few more hands would go up.
أراهن أن بضعة أيدي أخرى سترتفع
Even in this room, this is an issue that touches many of us,
حتى في هذه القاعة. إنها قضية تمس العديد منّا
and I am beginning to believe that we marginalize the issue
وأنا بدأت أعتقد أننا همّشنا القضية
because it does apply to us.
لأنها تنطبق علينا
Maybe it's easier to see in other zip codes
ربما لأنه من الأسهل رؤيتها موجهة للآخر
because we don't want to look at it.
لأننا لا نريد النظر إليها
We'd rather be sick.
بالأحرى نحن مرضى
Fortunately, scientific advances and, frankly, economic realities
لحسن الحظ، التقدم العلمي وبصراحة، الحقائق الاقتصادية
make that option less viable every day.
جعل هذا الخيار أقل قابلية للحياة كل يوم.
The science is clear:
العلم واضح
Early adversity dramatically affects health across a lifetime.
التعرض للعنف في وقت مبكر يؤثر بشكل كبير على الصحة مدى الحياة
Today, we are beginning to understand how to interrupt the progression
اليوم، نحن بدأنا نفهم كيف نوقف التقدم
from early adversity to disease and early death,
من التعرض المبكر للعنف إلى الأمراض والموت المبكر
and 30 years from now,
و ثلاثون سنة من الآن
the child who has a high ACE score
الطفل الذي لديه رصيد عالٍ من نقط ACE
and whose behavioral symptoms go unrecognized,
والذي تظهر أعراضه السلوكية غير المعترف بها،
whose asthma management is not connected,
ولديه علاج ضدّ الربو غير مرتبط
and who goes on to develop high blood pressure
ويصاب بارتفاع الضغط الدموي
and early heart disease or cancer
وأمراض القلب المبكرة أو السرطان
will be just as anomalous as a six-month mortality from HIV/AIDS.
سوف يكون مجرد ظاهرة غير عادية كالوفاة بعد ستة أشهر من فيروس نقص المناعة/الإيدز
People will look at that situation and say, "What the heck happened there?"
والناس سوف ينظرون إلى هذا الوضع ويقولون: "ماذا يحدث هناك؟"
This is treatable.
يمكن علاج هذا الأمر
This is beatable.
يمكن التغلب عليه
The single most important thing that we need today
وأهم شيء نحن بحاجة له اليوم
is the courage to look this problem in the face
هو الشجاعة لننظر إلى هذه المشكلة في الوجه
and say, this is real and this is all of us.
والقول: هذا حقيقي وهذا هو كل واحد منا
I believe that we are the movement.
أعتقد أننا الحركة
Thank you.
شكراً لكم
(Applause)
(تصفيق)